welcome back to the trt and hormone
optimization YouTube channel and back
with us as a guest is Ryan root welcome
back Ryan hey how are you Stephen thank
you thank you very much uh thank you
again uh for all the education that you
give everybody uh this channel is great
it really helps a lot of people and uh
we all appreciate what you do it's my
pleasure and it's h nice to have you
back with us so you came across a study
a study a very recent one in 2024 just
published and it's about um test Stone
and risk of clothing so um I'll put it
up on the screen and um you can share
your knowledge about
it okay yeah so this really helps put
into context um a lot of what we've been
learning uh over the over the years so
let me let me actually put this in the
context and start from the beginning I
want to do this chronologically so we
can kind of understand back about the
last study was about 10 years ago um and
before that there was a total of about
four studies that came out that
indicated testosterone
increased uh the risk for Venus um
thromboembolism which is blood cladding
right there wasn't it wasn't deeply
understood like what was what was
causing this risk all they said is that
we give people testosterone there's a
very small 10 out of 10,000 increased
risk for blood clading and that's all
that was said this is all the
information that was given now now two
of these studies found
that uh after six months the risk seemed
to normalize back to back to the zero
increase risk so after six months the
risk was back down to zero that was
never
explained um two of these studies found
that now there at the same time there
was three other studies that found no
global increase risk right and now since
then there has been multiple more
contemporary studies that have found no
increased risk of VTE or V Venus thrombo
embolism from
testosterone um so this study is
actually going to begin to elucidate
exactly uh why why there was an apparent
increase risk from two of these studies
sorry four of these studies back a
decade and more ago and exactly going to
elucidate exactly what's going on here
okay so now we'll just start with the
study okay so um we'll start with the
results here so hypog hypogonadal men
displayed significantly higher
endogenous thrombin potential so
thrombin is a clading factor one of the
many clading factors one of the problems
with um the previous studies is that um
it was not UND the the complex nature of
the of clading was not elucidated right
so it was just all they did was have a
vasile very fasile understanding
fibrinogen is a clading agent is what is
used in clats so hypogen men displayed
significantly higher endogenous thrombin
potential fibrinogen and significantly
lower antithrombin which is something
that reduces clots an antithrombin
levels both um before testosterone was
started and 6 months after testosterone
compared to healthy controls right hypog
metal men have more clotting factors and
less anti-clotting factors the ren peak
of hypog gatal men was significantly
higher than healthy controls six months
before
testosterone and but not at six months
after testosterone therapy um endogenous
testosterone potential and anti-in were
correlated with testosterone levels
right so the lower the testosterone
level The increased endogenous thrin
potential
um and the the less antithrombin which
reduces blood clamps okay so the
conclusion of this study and then we'll
go into the details is hypog hypogeal
men display Procol coagulant imbalance
detected by increasing thrombin
generation short-term trt does not
worsen Global coagulation suggesting
that the treatment can be safely
prescribed to men diagnosed with
hypogonadism okay so now we're going to
go into some of the details of exactly
what's going on here and we're going to
are to
elucidate um
why there was kind of some misconception
of
increased clading risk when people
started trt about 10 or more years ago
also what's important to understand here
is um is the the
current uh medical community's
understanding of clading right it's
pretty fasile all they all they
understand for all that they're trained
to look for is when your hemoglobin
hematocrit goes to a certain level or
your platelets go to a certain level um
that's what is going to Signal a risk
for clots um and they don't understand
all of the claing factors that go into
this and the complexity of it so in an
older
population what we have indicated here
is
that testosterone low testosterone is
increasing clouding factors which is
going to make um make our hemoglobin or
hemoglobin hematocrit is going to
increase and increase the risk of
cladding
so when a in the when your primary care
provider sees high hemoglobin High
hematocrit they tend to panic and say
you're going to have a stroke right this
is I hear it all the time patients
comeing to me my my primary career told
me that that I'm gonna have a stroke my
hemoglobin hocr is high you know we we
know this isn't true this is going to
elose a date exactly why it's not true
now um so another thing to understand is
that in in the older population we see
the risk of blood clots increase the
risk of Venus thromboembolism increase
um older people are on warrin we put
them on blood thinners um warrin what's
the other
one uh there's another one kumin warin
cinin blood thinners right to prevent
clots again this is going to elucidate
why
so in fact both testosterone and its
five Alpha reduced uh derivative
dihydrotestosterone exert an IM
inhibitory effect on primary primary
hemoo uh hemostasis by preventing a
Denine diphosphate mediated platelet
aggregation um this is also going to be
true for the rest of the androgens this
seems to be a function of Androgen I did
a deep dive on
stanazolol um earlier and stanazol also
has this effect where it
reduces uh clotting factors DHT does
this testosterone does it and it I'm
extrapolating to say that all androgens
will do this um and we're going to see
why here pretty soon more over
testosterone has an inhibitory effect on
coagulation and promotes fibr analysis
fibr analysis is the breakdown of
existing clots so this is actually
pretty big so this means that not only
are is testosterone reducing clotting
factors if you have a clot it will begin
breaking it down so this breaks down uh
existing clots consistently low
testosterone levels have been correlated
with increased platelet activity and
procoagulant profile current evidence
however has failed to provide that
part's that actually important um okay
okay so interestingly Studies by
Martinez at all and Walker all showed
this as an association reached a peak
within six months since the start of
treatment this is the two studies that I
said indicated that after six months the
risks seemed to disappear right um
nevertheless three
metaanalysis uh randomized controlled
trials did not find increased risk of
Venus thrombo eism as associated with
trt compared to Placebo this was the
older studies um that some of them
showed that there was an increased risk
and again that risk was very small some
of them showed that there was no
increased risk let's we're starting to
elucidate why there's an increased risk
okay so right here hypogonadal men
display a procoagulant imbalance
compared to age match healthy controls
right so healthy controls are people
with middle to upper quartile
testosterone
levels um kavousi at all reported an
increased risk of deep vein thrombosis
only in those hypogonadal patients
diagnosed on the basis of endocrine
Society guidelines receiving trt and
presenting their potential ideologies
for deep veinous
thrombosis after exclusion of these
cases the overall incidence of
thrombosis was similar to the general
population okay so what this is saying
that um
the studies that were done the two that
found or some of the the studies that
found that there was an increased risk
they used participants in the study that
had other reasons or ideologies for uh
thrombo embolism right so they had other
reasons why they would have a risk
whether it be like an injury or or just
an existing condition um you know like
um uh Factor five uh genetic mutation
and Factor five class agents like they
had some other reason why they would
have blood clot so when you exclude
those patients from these old studies
then there is no increased risk right um
so that's that's what they're saying
that the study was just poorly
performed and that's the those are the
ones that found an increased
risk um indeed some um thren Genesis
assay uh parameters that is thren peak
and velocity index are significant
higher in hypog hypogonadal men compared
to healthy control baselines but no
longer six months after trt so six
months after given trt
people's um clotting factors or
procoagulation agents um are normalized
to the same as people and with healthy
testosterone rages this observation may
suggest a trend towards the Improvement
of Po procoagulant imbalance following
trt but a longer time may be needed to
achieve normalization the need for a
longer time to attain parameter
normalization has already been observed
in the endocrine disorder characterized
by an increased throm
risk all
right
um so going down okay low testosterone
levels have been correlated with
increased platelet activity and
procoagulant
profile conversely both testosterone and
dihydrotestosterone have a inhibitory
effect on primary primary hemos stasis
as measured by the invitro test by
preventing adenosine D phosphate
mediated platelet aggregation right this
effect obtained directly by the
activation of the receptor on the
platelet membrane and indirectly through
the anti-aggregatory effect of Nitric o
oxide produced by the stimulation of
endothelial lining cells via the
Androgen receptor so this is saying that
testosterone itself has a direct effect
on platelets platelets have anden
receptors that pre that prevent clading
also skin the cells inside the veins
have Androgen receptors that when
received they increase nitrogen oxides
which um has a a vasal dilatory effect
which prevents clots as well right so
testosterone
itself
directly um affects the the coagulatory
factors and reduces
coagulation moreover testosterone
increases the expression of tissue
Factor pathway inhibitor and tissue
plasmagen activator and reduces the
secretion of plasmagen plasmagen
activator inhibitor thus inhibiting the
coagulation Cascade and promoting fibron
alysis so the entire the entire um
coagulation Cascade is inhibited by
testosterone and it also PR promotes
fibr analysis which is the breakdown of
existing classs
right um okay so this last
I I wanted to you know a lot of times
the the oh man there there's a a spot up
here that I just wanted to throw this in
um there's a spot up here that that
indicated a lot of the information about
the hypogonadal men and the hypo the
healthy controls that they have that
have middle to high range testosterone
levels and hypogonadal Men something of
interestes I just want to point out here
look at the BMI that they had for these
two so the in the the healthy control
had um most of their cohort was in a BMI
range of 18.5 to
24 while only one hypogonadal man was in
that
cohort and the the
hypogonadal the most in that cohort in
fact just about all of them were in a
range of of BMI of 25 all the way up to
grid and 40 right so this means this
this is more evidence that we have of
the that low testosterone causes
metabolic disorders and causes this
obesity most of the people were obese
who were in this hypogen class and you
know we've been taught the Antiquated
Notions um prior were that your
testosterone level could be low because
you're overweight because you're obese
right we now know that it's actually low
testosterone causes us to be obese it's
exactly the opposite and we see that
time and time again um low testosterone
causes metabolic disorders and people
are overweight and unhealthy that was
just kind of an interesting side but so
but obese people do seem to have a
little bit higher risk of clotting right
and so in order
to
dispel uh the notion that possibly these
over these obese people you know
the they're higher risk because they're
obese right and that's what this does
right here overweight and obese are
considered as comorbidities commonly
associated with myo honm and have a
higher prevalence in this population on
the other hand components of metabolic
syndrome including visceral added
opposed tissue can negatively affect
thromboembolic risk nevertheless it has
been shown that male hypogonadism has a
negative effect on U hemostasis per se
independently of the association with
metabolic syndrome so they're saying
that you know the coagulate the
increased coagulatory risk of
hypogonadism is independent of them
being overweight okay okay so what does
this all mean so what this means is that
there was a you know the study um
from the study from a decade or more ago
the studies from a decade or more ago
showed that uh we gave people
testosterone they seem to have a very
small increased risk you know in some of
the studies some of the studies showed
no risk but what was happening is now
that we now see this before I read the
study I knew that testosterone did not
increase the risk of clading but I
didn't know exactly why and I didn't
understand that testosterone ASC reduces
the risk of clading yeah
um so when when we
gave the problem was that we let people
go hypogonadal in the first place right
we let people go hypogonadal their
clotting risk came up then we gave them
testosterone which we know increases
hematocrit and hemoglobin right so when
we increase their clotting risk and then
increase their hemoglobin and hematocrit
you can see where there might be an
issue there right and it takes about six
months as we've seen for all of the
clotting risk the clading factors the
procoagulant to normalize so in that six
months the the some of the studies were
saying there is a slight increased risk
other studies were saying that there is
no Global increased risk but you can see
where there could be an issue the
problem is letting people go hypogonadal
in the first place yeah so you can be
proactive and make sure you never go
hypogonadal get on testosterone well
before you're at that hypogonadal stage
and and and then there's no increased
risk of of blood clots the the human
body is a symphony like we evolve to be
the symphony and you can see it right
like um when when we have when we we
give testosterone it increases our red
blood cells which increases hemoglobin
hemoglobin is what binds oxygen oxygen
is uh repl our body's ATP ATP ATP is our
body's currency for energy right so um
so increased red blood cells means more
oxygen equals energy right uh and when
so when we increase our red blood cells
with testosterone it increases the
production of epo which increases red
blood cells that's a good thing and our
body also reduces the risk of clading
because the testosterone has Direct
effects on the all the
procoagulation and inhibits coagulation
it's just a beautiful
the way this all works yeah um so so
that's the um so you know again all
these studies from a decade or more took
a very fasile look they just said oh um
here's we give people testosterone it
appears that there's a very small
increased risk therefore um testosterone
increases risk and again your your
primary care provider were taught that
the older population their increased
risk um for for cladding so if their
hemoglobin hematocrit goes above their
the range that's dangerous it could mean
that they CL without understanding the
deeper complexities of cladding so now
we now know that the through this the
the older population that are having
clotting issues is because their
testosterone is low if we if we gave
them testosterone before they ever went
hyetal they wouldn't have this clotting
risk and you can see it throughout you
know like all the nursing homes
throughout all the all these medical
issues you can see like all the Decay
and all the problems that low
testosterone is causing like the the
degeneration and the decay of everybody
as they age is largely due to low
hormones right yeah sure um yeah it's
very s surprising but um yeah it's very
nice uh to have explained by you because
we all knew this was the fact but we
didn't understand why so right very nice
uh study thank you for explaining it
yeah yeah absolutely it it did
hallucinate it uh for me uh as well so
it makes it makes it easier to explain
and makes it makes it understand why you
know why um having testosterone not only
does it not increase the risk but when
your hemoglobin hematocrit start to
increase a little bit it's a it's a good
thing until it gets to a certain point
right at a certain point we're gonna we
can start getting we're not worried
about increased risk of clats but we're
worried about increased um risk of
hypertension symptoms of hypertension
right but if we're just above the range
51 52 53
54% um
we're not worried right because that's
actually a decent range to be in and
your body is taking care the
testosterone is taking care of all the
clading
factors exactly so um we reassured now
there's no nothing to worry about just
for the people that are hippon and
starting trt in the first six months
maybe yeah right right and that um a lot
of the studies also showed that there
still was no global increase risk even
in that six month
but
um again some of the studies that showed
that they they were poorly run studies
they had they had patients who already
had other reasons other other a
theologies for for clotting so there was
other reasons why they would clot so
it's probably still not a risk even if
you're hypogonadal but that but again
you're right the key here is Never Let
Yourself Go hyp treat yourself well
before you're at that range um and you
know as we've seen
the most consistent benefits from
testosterone are found just above the
the normal range the normal testosterone
range so you want to keep yourself there
anyways yeah very clearly explained
thank you so much Brian yeah absolutely
thank you Dr Davis okay thanks for
coming back on the channel and uh talk
to you next time okay